

# Emma Ricart Bioinformatician & Developer

+41 78 206 99 46

emma.ricart89@gmail.com

in emma-ricart-phd-215028137

## Hard-skills

**Data analysis** 9+ yrs

**Software development** 8+ yrs.

Web development 7+ yrs.

## Soft-skills

- Learning agility
- Teamwork
- Communication skills
- Critical thinking
- Enthusiasm
- Initiative
- Trustworthiness
- Presentation skills

# Languages

English	C1
French	B1
Spanish & Catalan	C2

### **Profile**

Bioinformatician in the intersection of data analysis, pipeline design and software development. In the era of big data, my goal is to formulate data-driven hypothesis and validate them. I achieve this by 1) performing statistical analyses, 2) creating tools for data visualization, 3) developing pipelines or 4) building computational infrastructures such as databases. I hold a a PhD in Bioinformatics and I conducted interdisciplinary research working with biologists, physicists and software engineers. I'm deeply committed to promoting best programming practices for shareable and reproducible research!

## Work experience

#### Bioinformatician | Database administrator

02/2021 - 02/2024

Bassani Lab (Prof. Michal Bassani)

**♀** AGORA Cancer Research Center - Lausanne

- Developed a workflow for large-scale identification and quantification of HLAI/HLAII peptides from mass spectrometry experiments
- Implemented an ETL process for the creation of an immunopeptidomics data warehouse which included  $\pm 1.000.000$  peptides identified with the workflow
- Used the collected data to create a scoring system for the prioritization of neoantigens, directly impacting the clinical trials
- Build a web interface for querying and visualizing the database

Python – R – Bash – Nextflow – HPC – Immunopeptidomics – Mass spectrometry – Data Visualization – Biological Data Analysis – Docker – Software development – Git

#### Ph.D. Student

09/2015 - 09/2019

Proteomic Informatics Group (Frederique Lisacek)

Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics (SIB) - Geneva

- Developed rBAN, a java package and web application tool for the retro biosynthesis of non-ribosomal peptides
- Developed NRPro, a web application tool for the identification and annotation of tandem mass spectra from peptidic natural products
- Worked with SMILES format and graph structures for the substructures search and the fragmentation algorithms used by the tools
- Build a NoSQL database for the backend of NRPro integrating data from Norine, ChEBI and Natural Products Atlas

□ Java – R – Maven – MongoDB – AngularJS – Mass spectrometry – Peptidomics – Data Visualization – Biological Data Analysis – Software development – Git

#### Junior Bioinformatician

02/2015 - 09/2015

The Chuang Lab (Prof. Jeffrey H. Chuang)

**♀** JAX Cancer Center - Connecticut

- Analyzed iCLIP data from ENCODE project to study RNA-protein binding sides

Python – R – Perl – Bash – HPC – Biological Data Analysis – Statistics – Data Visualization – Transcriptomics

#### **Bioinformatics researcher**

09/2014 - 02/2015

Computational Genomics group (Prof. Eduardo Eyras)

PRBB - Barcelona

- Analyzed and quantified iTRAQ mass spectrometry data from the TCGA project to validate findings identified at RNA level

# **Programming**

- Python
- ▶ R
- Bash
- Nextflow
- Java
- Perl
- Javascript
- ▶ HTML & CSS

## Server side

- Docker & Conda
- MongoDB & PostGreSQL
- Tomcat
- Node.js
- REST API
- HPC

# Frameworks/Libs

- Django
- AngularJS
- React & Next.js
- Bootstrap & MatierialUI
- JUnit

# **Development** tools

- Maven
- Git
- Jenkins

#### Master's Student

Computational Proteomics group (Fredrik Levander)

Lund University - Sweden

- Identified and quantified of protein variants using a combination of shotgun proteomics and DIA I C-MS
- Applied statistical analysis to the proteins identified for biomarkers discovery

### **Education**

#### Ph.D. in Bioinformatics

Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics (SIB) University of Geneva

Master's degree in Biomedical engineering

University of Barcelona Polytechnic University of Catalonia Lund University

Bachelor's degree in Biotechnology

University of Vic - Central University of Catalonia

09/2015 - 09/2019

02/2014 - 06/2014

09/2012 - 09/2014

09/2007 - 09/2011

## **Awards**

Winner Best Lighting Talk Award

SIB Days Awards 2018

SIB PhD Fellowship Laureate

SIB Fellowship Program 2015

Fundació Agrupació Master's Degree Grant

Fundació Agrupació Awards 2013

2015

2018

2013

## Relevant publications

<u>Ricart, Emma</u>, Maude Pupin, Markus Muller, and Frédérique Lisacek. Automatic annotation and dereplication of tandem mass spectra of peptidic natural products. *Analytical Chemistry*, 92(24):15862–15871, 2020.

Ricart, Emma, Valérie Leclère, Areski Flissi, Markus Mueller, Maude Pupin, and Frédérique Lisacek. rban: retro-biosynthetic analysis of nonribosomal peptides. *Journal of cheminformatics*, 11(1):1–14, 2019.

Areski Flissi, <u>Ricart, Emma</u>, Clémentine Campart, Mickael Chevalier, Yoann Dufresne, Juraj Michalik, Philippe Jacques, Christophe Flahaut, Frédérique Lisacek, Valérie Leclère, et al. Norine: update of the nonribosomal peptide resource. *Nucleic acids research*, 48(D1):D465–D469, 2020.

Markus Müller, Florian Huber, Marion Arnaud, Anne Kraemer, <u>Altimiras, Emma Ricart,</u> Justine Michaux, Marie Taillandier-Coindard, Johanna Chiffelle, Baptiste Murgues, Talita Gehret, et al. Machine learning methods and harmonized datasets improve immunogenic neoantigen prediction. *Immunity*, 56(11):2650–2663, 2023.

Anne Kraemer, Chloe Chong, Florian Huber, HuiSong Pak, Brian J Stevenson, Markus Müller, Justine Michaux, <u>Altimiras, Emma Ricart</u>, Sylvie Rusakiewicz, Laia Simó-Riudalbas, et al. The immunopeptidome landscape associated with t cell infiltration, inflammation and immune editing in lung cancer. *Nature Cancer*, pages 1–21, 2023.